<module name="open_source_tools_drift">
<spec id="purpose">STUB. Drift is a spec-code sync tool for LLM-era development. Tracks the relationship between specification terms (specs) and the code that implements them (markers); surfaces divergence when either side changes. See <ref spec="business_goals.build_open_source_tools">building open source tools</ref>. To be expanded when the output-layer work (PLAN.md) lands and references these specs from output_intent.*.</spec>
<spec id="spec_code_sync_model">STUB. The methodology drift implements and demonstrates: specifications live as plain XML; code regions are wrapped by D! id=... range-start/range-end comment markers; specs and markers are linked; drift detects when either side changes and forces per-edge review before resolution. See <ref spec="open_source_tools_drift.purpose">drift's purpose</ref> and <ref spec="principles.friction">friction-as-feature</ref>.</spec>
<spec id="developer_persona">STUB. The interactive human developer using drift at a terminal: writes specs, places markers, runs `drift todo`, reads `drift diff` output, resolves edges one at a time with `drift reset`. Needs legible, scannable terminal output — color-coded status, clear diff presentation, low-friction review. See <ref spec="open_source_tools_drift.purpose">drift's purpose</ref>.</spec>
<spec id="ci_persona">STUB. CI/automation pipelines consuming drift as a quality gate: invoke `drift todo` for its exit code (0=clean, 1=drift, 2=error), parse output, integrate with build systems. Needs reliable exit codes, stable output format, pipe-safe behavior (no ANSI escapes when redirected). See <ref spec="open_source_tools_drift.purpose">drift's purpose</ref>.</spec>
<spec id="llm_agent_persona">STUB. LLM coding agents consuming drift to self-verify against specs before claiming "done." Instead of trusting "tests passed," an agent runs `drift todo` to confirm every spec is still satisfied by the code it modified. Needs structured, parseable output — JSON, not regex over human prose. This is the concrete instance of the explore_and_discover goal: a new development workflow that LLMs enable. See <ref spec="open_source_tools_drift.purpose">drift's purpose</ref> and <ref spec="business_goals.explore_and_discover">exploring new workflows LLMs enable</ref>.</spec>
<spec id="dual_audience_constraint">STUB. Drift's output must serve both human audiences (developer_persona, ci_persona) and machine audiences (llm_agent_persona, ci_persona) from a single codebase, without forcing one to accommodate the other. Each command's output must be available in modes appropriate to each audience: color for interactive terminals, plain for pipes and redirected output, JSON for programmatic consumption. This constraint is the parent commitment that output_intent.* specs break down into specific modes. Synthesizes developer_persona, ci_persona, and llm_agent_persona.</spec>
</module>
